Guide to the Ursule Molinaro Papers MSS.514
Fales Library and Special Collections
Ursule Molinaro Papers
1942-2004
Fales Library and Special Collections
Molinaro, Ursule
MSS.514
13.95 Linear Feet in 11 record cartons, 3 manuscript boxes, 1 small box, 1 CD box, and 1 flat file folder
11.8 Megabytes in 116 files
Ursule Molinaro (1916-2000) was a poet, playwright, and visual artist who moved from France to New York City in the early 1950s to be a translator at the United Nations. Molinaro began publishing her writing in the 1960s and taught classes on creative writing before her death on July 10, 2000. This collection consists of correspondence between 1942 and 2004, as well as manuscripts of novels, plays, short stories. Materials also include flyers and other ephemera promoting Molinaro's writing and painting, audiovisual recordings of Molinaro reading her work, and photographic prints, negatives, and slides.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes correspondence, ephemera, and manuscripts of novels, plays, and short stories by Ursule Molinaro between 1963 and 1997. Molinaro's manuscripts focus on reimagining Greek myths to give the female characters individual agency to escape the social strictures of their society. Ursule's writing material ranges from early research and handwritten notes to the final published books and plays. Her correspondence, from 1942 to 2000, are about translations and contracts related to publishing her writing and exhibiting her paintings. The collection also includes flyers, brochures promoting Ursule Molinaro's writing and painting from 1981 to 1994, and photographic prints, negatives, and slides. Audiovisual recordings of Molinaro reading her work as well as performances by contemporary artists she admired, like Arlo Guthrie and Ursula K. Le Guin, are included in the Ursule Molinaro Papers.
Biographical Note
Ursule Molinaro (1916-2000) was a poet, playwright, and visual artist who moved from France to New York City in 1949 and became a translator at the United Nations in 1951. She taught classes on creative writing at New York University and the University of Hawaii. She began publishing her writing in the 1960s and much of her work focuses on reimagining Greek myths for a contemporary audience. Molinaro died in New York City on July 10, 2000.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Bruce Benderson, 2017. The accession number associated with this gift is 2017.184
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact fales.library@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Manuscripts; Playwriting.; Mythology, Greek, in literature; Women and literature; Women authors; American drama -- Women authors; Authors; Dramatists, American.
- Unresolved Manuscripts, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- Correspondence, 1978-1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- The Sundial, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Manuscripts, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- San Francisco is a State of Mind, Death to the Deserving, 1973-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Short Stories, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Tyrants, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The Replacement and That Which is Bright Rises Twice, 1974-1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Photos by Alix Jeffry, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
- Liable Acts of God, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Dream Rebel, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
- Ghosts of Leaves on Winter Trees, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Jonquils for Narcissus, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Incomplete Collection of Stories, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Correspondence and Contracts, 1974-2000 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Fliers, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Saint Boy, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
- The Great Emancipation, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24-29)
- Needlepoint, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Saviors and Their Prey and Speculative Manipulators, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Sweet Cheat of Freedom, 1971-1991 (Box 1, Folder 32-33)
- Manuscripts, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Hex-Agon, Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Manuscripts, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Analects of Self Contempt, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Manuscripts, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Fat Skeletons Reviews, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Fat Skeletons Correspondence, 1989-1998 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
- Fat Skeletons Reviews and Corrections, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Fat Skeletons, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8-18)
- Helen Mar Sale, 1963-1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Postcards, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Folder 2, Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Folder 3, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Folder 4, Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Folder 5, Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Folder 6, Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Folder, Reviews and Criticism, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Folder, Readings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Chelsea 8, 1960-10 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Folder, Publications, Undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Folder 10, Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Folder 11, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
- The New Moon With the Old Moon in Her Arms, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 34-35, Box 7, Folder 1-2)
- Pythagoras My Love, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Angel on Fire, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Unresolved Notes and Manuscript, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Research for Pythagoras My Love, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Research for a Saint Recycled, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
- After the Wash, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- The Engagement, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Breakfast Past Noon, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- A Full Moon of Women, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Baby Prelude/Baby Battle, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Marriage is a Long Deep Freeze, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- The Historical Day of Charlotte d'Armant, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Friends of Mine No Longer, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
- An Unfinished Letter, 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Notes and Research on Cortez, 1987-1991 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Dreams of the Waning Moon, Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
- The Baby Prelude, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- The Contest, 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- A Saint Recycles, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Apocalyptic Flirtations, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- A Diet of Worms, Undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
- The Tourniquet, 1970-1987 (Box 3, Folder 25, Flat-file-folder 3 Right)
- A Marriage in Progress, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 26-27)
- Antiques, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Tyrants, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 29-31)
- The New Moon with the Old Moon in her Arms, 1983-1994 (Box 3, Folder 32-34)
- Reassembling a Lady Named Fred, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Marco Pogo's Tale of a Cat That Has No Tail, 1976-1993 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- The Parent Plays, 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- The Mine, 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Innocent, Undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
- The Parent Plays, 1976-1982 (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
- Fat Skeletons, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6-12)
- Mirrors for Small Beasts, Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Unresolved Manuscripts & Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
- The Happy Hexagon, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 15-22)
- Assorted Acrostics, Undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Innocent, Undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Tyrants, Undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
- The Contest, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Spring 1983, Undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
- The Thirteenth Christmas, Undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
- The Good Daughter, Undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
- The Sunday Ride, Undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Shadowplay On Snow, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Suppertime, Undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Pieke Bierman, Violetta, Undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Application Forms, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Correspondence, 1970-1988 (Box 4, Folder 35-42)
- Correspondence, 1961-2000 (Box 5, Folder 1-10)
- Unresolved Manuscripts, Undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Folder #2, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Dreams, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Pythagoras, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Folder #4, 1984-1995 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Theatre Correspondence, 1978-1987 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- The Autobiography of Cassandra, Undated (Box 5, Folder 17-23)
- Poetry Publications, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Unresolved Manuscripts, Undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Avifauna, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Rat Mother, 1992-1995 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- The Houseguest, Undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Worry Patterns of Geometry, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Primitive Practices, Undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
- The Privileged Pain of Sacrifice, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Imported Smiles, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Father Ozwald's Do-It-Yourself Martyrdom Kit, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Amazons in the Night City, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Architecture of Intellegence, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 35)
- Doomed Survivors, Undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Solitary, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 37)
- The Hanging of my Maid Mildred Mulligan, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 38)
- Pet, Undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
- When the Iceman Came, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 40)
- Farmed Out, Undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
- Margot, Queen of Love, Undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
- The Watcher, 1942-2004 (Box 5, Folder 43)
- The Morality of the 7 Deadly Sins, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 44)
- On the Other Side of the Door, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Unattainable, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Live Ash from Burned Witches, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Radio Activity, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Bird of Ambush, 1987-1992 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Mating Calls, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Kaiulani Avenue, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- The Chemistry of Miracles, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Rites of a Non-Requital, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- The Happy Hexagon, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Burial Rites, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Incubus, Undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
- April in Paris, Undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
- A Fortaste of Eternity, Undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
- The Only Child, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- The Time When the Moon Rises, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- The Night Dog, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- One Chink in Her Perfect Armor, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Epilogue to a Beautiful Sister, Undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Merdeka Forever, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Shimmer, Undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Out of the Dark Room, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Invasions of Privacy, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Re Reading Balzac, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Phamily Alphabet, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Power Dreamers, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 26-27)
- Coupling Rod, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Self Portrait in Waining Winter Light, Undated (Box 6, Folder 29)
- A Scenic Train Ride into the Past, 1992-1994 (Box 6, Folder 30)
- Rites of Non-Requital, 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 31)
- Teen Machine, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 32)
- A Xmas Tryst, 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Lying Loveless in the House of Men, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 34)
- Bird in Ambush, 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 35)
- Persistence of Matter, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 36)
- Inescapable Heloise, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 37)
- Ghost Collage, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 38)
- The Mortality of the 7 Deadly Sins, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 39)
- 3 Women on the Stairs, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 40)
- The Seeing Eye Witness, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 41)
- Betrayal: the Ultimate Indictment, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 42)
- Leaving for the Hero's Life, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 43)
- Recycling the Past, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 44)
- Amber, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 45)
- A Knight with No Armor, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 46)
- Iphigenia, 1990-1996 (Box 6, Folder 47)
- The Body Around the Voice, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 48)
- Coda to A Conversation By Ida Frank, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 49)
- Autopsy of a Dead Relationship, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 50)
- Revenge for Bosnia, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 51)
- Weekend Streets, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 52)
- Pigeon in A Pit, 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 53)
- Dream Rebel, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 54-56)
- Correspondence, 1952-1999 (Box 6, Folder 57)
- Folder #1, Undated (Box 6, Folder 58)
- Prison Architects, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 3-5)
- The Happy Hexagon, Undated (Box 7, Folder 6-8)
- Fliers/Brochures/Press Releases, 1981-1994 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1989-1991 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- The Happy Hexagon, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
- Folder, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- The Great Emancipation, Undated (Box 8, Folder 6-10)
- Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 11-13)
- Sony videotape, Readings by Ursule Molinaro, Undated (Box 9)
- Reel to reel tape, unknown, forwarded by CBC Radio Canada, Undated (Box 9)
- Blue 8-track, Undated (Box 9)
- VHS, Tyrant production, Bristol Community College, Undated (Box 9)
- Reel to reel Summer Song, 1974-05-30 (Box 9)
- 8-track Buffalo Reading, 1978-10-15 (Box 9)
- Scotch reel to reel tape, unknown, Undated (Box 9)
- 8-track reading of [illegible], Undated (Box 9)
- Cassette, profile of UM, 1975-10-13 (Box 9)
- VHS A profile of UM by Kate Sample, Undated (Box 9)
- Tropsimes, Nathalie Sarratue; The Insufficent Rope, Ursule Molinaro, Side 2: Prayer Wheels, UM, Undated (Box 9)
- Blank Recording, Undated (Box 9)
- Blank Recording, Undated (Box 9)
- Pierre Hardoy!, Undated (Box 9)
- Sweet Cheat of Freedom, 14th Street, 1974-05-30 (Box 9)
- "Ecrivains Etrangers" Ursule Monilaro, Undated (Box 9)
- Lisa Meitner, Undated (Box 9)
- The Pheonix Fire Mystery, Undated (Box 9)
- Astrology Reading By Susan Duncan, 1990-02-13 (Box 9)
- Astrology Reading By Susan Duncan, 1991-07-07 (Box 9)
- Music and Poetry of the Kesh, Undated (Box 9)
- Blank 8-Track, Undated (Box 9)
- Cassette, New Letters on The Air: Ursule Molinaro, Undated (Box 9)
- Reel to reel, Mirrors for Small Beasts, Read by Jack Bachem, Undated (Box 9)
- Reel to reel, unlabled, Undated (Box 9)
- Reel to reel, Arlo Guthrie, Undated (Box 9)
- Reel to reel, Antiques, Undated (Box 9)
- Reel to reel, [illegible] John Monkey Plug, Undated (Box 9)
- Manuscript Fragments, Undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
- Poems Folder 3, 1983-1984 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Poems Folder 4, Undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Folder 5, Undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
- Folder 10, Undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Acrostics, Undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Manuscripts, Undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 10, Folder 13-16)
- The Virility Factor, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 17)
- The Virility Factor, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 18)
- The Virility Factor, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 19-21)
- Correspondence and Fliers, 1984 - 1994 (Box 10, Folder 22)
- the Rented Summer, Undated (Box 10, Folder 23)
- The Rented Summer, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Astrology, Undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Fat Skeletons, Undated (Box 11, Folder 3-6)
- Works By Other, 1985-1991 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Newspaper Works By Other, 1967-1993 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Works By Other, 1959-1997 (Box 11, Folder 9-11)
- Ou Sont Les Hippocampes, 1981-1982 (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Shadowman & Sunshine, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 13-14)
- Correspondence and Contracts, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 15)
- Publications, Undated (Box 11, Folder 16-20)
- Handwritten Notes, 1942-1991 (Box 11, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1997-2000 (Box 11, Folder 22)
- Work of Others, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 23-25)
- German Monika Treut Scripts, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 26)
- On Immigration, Undated (Box 11, Folder 27)
- The Prison Architects, Undated (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
- Collected Reviews, 1954-1983 (Box 12, Folder 4-9)
- New Moon With The Old Moon in Its Arms Review, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Folder 2, Undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Hawaii Materials, 1980-1985 (Box 12, Folder 12-13)
- Collected Reviews, 1967-1993 (Box 12, Folder 14-15)
- Articles on Ursule, 1962-1981 (Box 12, Folder 16-17)
- Stories, Undated (Box 12, Folder 18)
- Giocasta La Regina (in Italian) by UM, Undated (Box 12)
- CDR disks of UM's Word/Word Perfect Files, 2001
  - Physical Disks (Box 12)
  - Digital Files, FA_MSS_514_ER_1
- The Curse of the Endless Living, Undated (Box 12, Folder 19-20)
- Angel on Fire, Undated (Box 12, Folder 21)
- The Best American Short Stories 1963 (Box 12, Folder 22)
- Cassandra, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 23)
- Sounds of a Drunken Summer, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 24)
- Fat Skeletons, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 25)
- The Zodiac Lovers, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 26)
- Publications, 1958-1979 (Box 12, Folder 27)
- Chelsea, 1959-1965 (Box 13, Folder 1-5)
- That Which is Bright Rises Twice, Undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Manuscripts, 1964-1993 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Personal Correspondence, 1955-2000 (Box 13, Folder 8-10)
- Publication and Reviews, 1971-1989 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Manuscript Fragment, Undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Slides of Paintings, Undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Vitaleyeser Magazine, Undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Photographs, Undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Caprice Magazine, 1999-2000 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Correspondence and Reviews, 1952-1999 (Box 14, Folder 8)
- I Ching, Undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Marco Pago, 1976-1983 (Box 14, Folder 11)
- Mounted Transparencies Number 20, circa 1970-1990 (Box 14, Folder 12)
- Robert and Amy, undated (Box 14, Folder 13)
- Diane's Photos of Ursule, undated (Box 14, Folder 14)
- Neary, undated (Box 14, Folder 15)
- Ursule Molinaro Slides, undated (Box 14, Folder 16)
- [Unlabeled Slides], undated (Box 14, Folder 17)
- Slide Viewer (Box 15)